Guide to the Dudley Poore Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dudley Poore papers
1840-1975
YCAL MSS 599
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
23.36
(57 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, notebooks and diaries, writings, photographs, and other materials documenting the personal and professional life of American poet and author Dudley Poore. Poore was part of a circle of writers at Harvard University that included e.e. cummings, John Dos Passos, Robert Hillyer, Robert Stewart Mitchell, and Cuthbert Wright, and the correspondence features letters with these associates, as well as John Peale Bishop, Dudley Fitts, Robert Finch, Arthur K. McComb, Katherine Anne Porter, and others. The correspondence includes approximately 850 letters from Poore to his parents, much of which dates from Poore's days as a student and his service in the Army Ambulance Corps and Red Cross during World War One. Notebooks and diaries contain journal entries, drafts of literary projects and correspondence, travel logs, and student notebooks, as well as diaries Poore kept while serving in Europe during the war. The collection also contains drafts of writings, family and personal photographs, and other papers.
Poore, Dudley
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on various funds, 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Dudley Poore (1893-1981)
Dudley Poore, American author and translator, was the son of Alvin B. and Mary L. Poore. He was educated at Harvard University prior to the First World War and, during the war, served in the Army Ambulance Corps and Red Cross. Poetry by Poore is included in Eight Harvard Poets (1917) and his translations of Spanish and Portugese works include Our Daily Bread (1943) by Enrique Gil Gilbert and The Bonfire (1944) by Cecilio J. Carneiro. Poore also co-edited the selections Fiesta in November: Stories fron Latin America (1942) and Cuentistas norteamericanos (1946).
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence, notebooks and diaries, writings, photographs, and other materials documenting the personal and professional life of American poet and author Dudley Poore. Poore was part of a circle of writers at Harvard University before WWI that included e.e. cummings, John Dos Passos, Robert Hillyer, Robert Stewart Mitchell, and Cuthbert Wright, published together in Eight Harvard Poets (1917), and the correspondence features letters with these associates, as well as John Peale Bishop, Dudley Fitts, Robert Finch, Arthur K. McComb, Katherine Anne Porter, and others. The correspondence also includes approximately 850 letters from Poore to his parents, much of which dates from Poore's days as a student and his service in the Army Ambulance Corps and Red Cross during the war. Notebooks and diaries contain daily journal entries, drafts of literary projects and correspondence, travel logs, and student notebooks, as well as diaries Poore kept while serving in Europe during the war. The collection also contains drafts of writings, family and personal photographs, and other papers.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1915-1975. II. Notebooks and Diaries, 1906-1970s. III. Writings, 1927-1940s. IV. Photographs, 1840s-1969. V. Other Papers, [circa 1915-1940s].
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, American; Photographic prints; Authors; Bishop, John Peale, 1892-1944; Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1894-1962; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970; Finch, Robert, 1900-1995; Fitts, Dudley, 1903-1968; Hillyer, Robert, 1895-1961; McComb, Arthur K. (Arthur Kilgore), 1895-; Mitchell, Stewart, 1892-1957; Poore, Dudley; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980; Wright, Cuthbert; American Red Cross; Harvard University; United States. Army ( Ambulances)
- Correspondence, 1910-1975; Series I; 7.51; (19 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries for General and Family Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence features correspondence with authors, publishers, and Poore's family. Poore was part of a small circle of writers at Harvard University before WWI, including e.e. cummings, John Dos Passos, Robert Hillyer, Robert Stewart Mitchell, and Cuthbert Wright, published together in Eight Harvard Poets (1917). General Correspondence features letters from these Harvard associates, as well as John Peale Bishop, Dudley Fitts, Robert Finch, Arthur K. McComb, Katherine Anne Porter, and others.
  General Correspondence includes some third-party correspondence. Unsorted correspondence is listed at the end of the alphabetical run of named correspondents.
  Family correspondence features approximately 850 pieces of correspondence from Poore to his parents, Alvin and Mary Poore, much of which dates from Poore's days as a student at Harvard and his service in the Army Ambulance Corps and Red Cross during the war.
  - General Correspondence
    - Bishop, John Peale, 1941-1944 (Box 1)
    - Bridell, Henschel, 1946 June 20 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Slater, 1921 November 19 (Box 1)
    - Coolidge, Richard (Box 1)
    - Cope, Tom (Box 1)
    - Copeland, C. T., 1915 (Box 1)
    - Coyne, Joan, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
    - Crawford, Berenice (Box 1)
    - Cubie, Grete W., 1975 December 28 (Box 1)
    - Cummings, E. E., 2 (Box 1)
    - Dos Passos, [Betty?] (Box 1)
    - Dos Passos, John, 2 (Box 1)
    - Fairbanks, Sidney, 1919 April 16 (Box 1)
    - Farrar & Rinehart, 1941-1944 (Box 2)
    - Finch, Robert, 5 (Box 2)
    - Finch, Robert (continued), 6 (Box 3)
    - Fitts, Dudley, 1941-1943 (Box 3)
    - Fruge, Grete, 2 (Box 4)
    - Hazeltine, Jennie B., 2 (Box 4)
    - Hillyer, Robert (Box 4)
    - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1941-1944; 2 (Box 4)
    - Kahler, Wood (Box 4)
    - Knopf, Alfred A., 1941-1944 (Box 4)
    - Laird, L. G., 1919 December 27 (Box 4)
    - Landsberg, Melvin (Box 5)
    - Lawson, Adelaide (Box 5)
    - Lecomte, ---- (Box 5)
    - Lippmann, Walter (Box 5)
    - McComb, Arthur K., 5 (Box 5)
    - McComb, Arthur K. (continued), 6 (Box 6)
    - McComb, Arthur K. (continued), 3 (Box 7)
    - McComb, Arthur K. to John Dos Passos (Box 7)
    - McIntosh, E. M., 1918 (Box 7)
    - McKinnon, Cecilia, 1930-1933 (Box 7)
    - McLeish, Richard, 1941 (Box 7)
    - Millett, Betty, 1917-1919 (Box 7)
    - Mitchell, R. Stewart, 1916; 2 (Box 7)
    - Mitchell, R. Stewart (continued) (Box 8)
    - Morrison, Ted, 1939 (Box 8)
    - Morse, Robert, 1915-1920 (Box 8)
    - Murphy, Gerald; Murphy, Sara (Box 8)
    - Nagel, Edward (Box 8)
    - Nathan Robert, 1916 February 28 (Box 8)
    - Perry, Constance, 1917 (Box 8)
    - Platt, Richard (Box 8)
    - Porter, Katherine Anne (Box 8)
    - Rickel, William (Box 8)
    - Roberts, George, 1922 April 22 (Box 8)
    - Schnakenberg, Henry (Box 8)
    - State Department, 1943-1944 (Box 8)
    - Stearns, Harold C., 1919 January 23 (Box 8)
    - Stillwell, M. C. (Box 8)
    - Strong, Leonard A. G., 1923 July (Box 8)
    - Sweeney, ---- (Box 8)
    - Translations (Box 9)
    - Van der Arend, Frederick (Box 9)
    - Walcott, John (Box 9)
    - Watson, Forbes (Box 9)
    - Watson, Sibley, 2 (Box 9)
    - Woollcott, Alexander (Box 9)
    - Wright, Cuthbert (Box 9)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 3 (Box 9)
    - Unsorted correspondence (continued), 8 (Box 10)
    - Unsorted correspondence (continued), 2 (Box 11)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (parents), [circa 1910-1944]; 3 (Box 11)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 6 (Box 12)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 5 (Box 13)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 5 (Box 14)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 5 (Box 15)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 5 (Box 16)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 6 (Box 17)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 5 (Box 18)
    - Poore, Alvin B. and Mary L. (continued), [circa 1910-1944]; 3 (Box 19)
- Notebooks and Diaries, [1906-1970s]; Series II; 5.42; (13 boxes, 1 folder)
  Materials arranged as received by the library.
  Series II. Notebooks and Diaries contains journals, drafts of literary projects and correspondence, travel logs, and lecture notebooks, as well as diaries Poore kept while serving in Europe during the First World War.
  - Notebooks and Diaries, 10 (Box 20)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 14 (Box 21)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 7 (Box 22)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 7 (Box 23)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 7 (Box 24)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 11 (Box 25)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 13 (Box 26)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 7 (Box 27)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 8 (Box 28)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 11 (Box 29)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 10 (Box 30)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 14 (Box 31)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued), 11 (Box 32)
  - Notebooks and Diaries (continued) (Box 33)
- Writings, 1927-[1940s?]; Series III; 3.55; (9 boxes)
  Writings arranged as received by the library.
  Series III. Writings consists chiefly of works by Poore, but includes writings by others. Poore's writings include drafts of poems, short stories, plays, novels, translations, and a memoir of his years as a student at Harvard University.
  Unsorted and identified writings can be found at the end of the writings listed by title.
  - The Pipes of Pan (Box 33)
  - La Busca (Box 33)
  - Mother Knows (Box 33)
  - How They Came To Be Mummies (Box 33)
  - Colors (Box 33)
  - Dodie (Box 33)
  - Thoughts on the Character of Francis Thompson (Box 33)
  - Parody of Pound's Cantos by Dos Passos, Mitchell and Poore (Box 33)
  - Poetry ms. (Box 33)
  - DP's rough draft, letters to John Dos Passos (Box 33)
  - New Yorker publications by others (Box 33)
  - The Lake (Box 33)
  - She walked quickly up to the house between the trim rows (Box 33)
  - Good-bye, Nimne (Box 33)
  - About Mama Green (Box 33)
  - Ode in the Time of Battle (Box 34)
  - Breakfast in Bed (Box 34)
  - Good-bye, Lola Darling (Box 34)
  - Stories by Cecilio J. Carneiro (Box 34)
  - A Legacy (Box 34)
  - A Pudding, 2 (Box 34)
  - Notes for The Portable House, The End of a Friendship, The Man Who Discovered an Italian Town, The Watchdogs (Box 34)
  - "Macbeth": Its History, Philosophy and Prophecy (Box 34)
  - From Homeward Songs by the Way (Box 34)
  - Neighbors, MJP's Early Homes (Box 34)
  - Eustace Diamonds, 2 (Box 35)
  - At Miss Laird's, 3 (Box 35)
  - Legend of Lavinia (Box 35)
  - Verano de Membrillas (Box 35)
  - Friendship Won't Stand That by Townsend Ludington (Box 36)
  - The Fourth Ward, 2 (Box 36)
  - The Two Images (Box 36)
  - The Pipes of Pan, Gala Night (Box 36)
  - The Raffle, 2 (Box 36)
  - Royal Progress, Life of a Ghost, Breakfast in Bed (Box 36)
  - Autumn Butterflies (Box 36)
  - Romance by Wieniawski (Box 36)
  - On the Wing and other writings (Box 36)
  - On the Wing, A Pudding (Box 36)
  - The Far-Off Isle: A Dramatic Interlude, The Death of Ailell: A Play in One Act (Box 36)
  - Palermo (Box 36)
  - Drafts of Poore's Spanish memoir (Box 36)
  - There Stands a Tree (Box 36)
  - Untitled play (Box 36)
  - In the Picas (Box 36)
  - Phoebe Tuttle (Box 37)
  - [Summer?], 1927 (Box 37)
  - Rough Draft Recounting My First Arrival in Spain, First Draft of Miss Laird's (Box 37)
  - Looking Down From the Bedroom Window (Box 37)
  - Mrs. Eddowes, 2 (Box 37)
  - Young Curator (Box 37)
  - Miss Ramsay, 2 (Box 37)
  - Writings by others (Box 38)
  - Short stories, miscellaneous, 3 (Box 38)
  - Short stories, miscellaneous (continued) (Box 39)
  - Short stories and poems, miscellaneous, 2 (Box 39)
  - Poems, miscellaneous, 7 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous drafts, 7 (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous drafts (continued), 6 (Box 41)
- Photographs, 1840s-1969; Series IV; 5.38; (12 boxes)
  Series IV. Photographs contains photographs, negatives, and printed material. There are images of Poore, Robert Finch, and others and examples of early photographic processes, such as tintypes, daguerrotypes, and photographs on glass.
  - Photographs, 12 (Box 42)
  - Photographs (continued), 16 (Box 43)
  - Photographs (continued), 12 (Box 44)
  - Robert Finch, photographs, 2 (Box 44)
  - Pete and his mistress (Box 44)
  - Cedar Hurst (Box 44)
  - Dudley Poore (Box 44)
  - Mlle. Levy (Box 44)
  - Printed material (Box 44)
  - Photo album (Box 45)
  - Photo slides (Box 46)
  - Photo slides (continued) (Box 47)
  - Germany, negatives and prints, 1969 August (Box 47)
  - Negatives and prints, 4 (Box 47)
  - Florida with Russ, sheet negatives, 1957 January (Box 47)
  - Sheet negatives, 13 (Box 48)
  - Sheet negatives (continued), 5 (Box 49)
  - Swan Cove, sheet negative (Box 49)
  - Everglade rookery, sheet negatives (Box 49)
  - Murphy pars I and II, sheet negatives (Box 49)
  - Portrait: Mary Brodwell, sheet negatives (Box 49)
  - Portrait: Steve, sheet negatives (Box 49)
  - Tintypes, unidentified photographer (Box 50)
  - Daguerrotypes, unidentified photographer, 1840s-1850s (Box 51)
  - Photographs on glass, [circa 1890s] (Box 52)
  - Rolled negatives, 1930s (Box 53)
- Other Papers, [circa 1915-1940s]; Series V; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Materials arranged in the order in which they were received by the library.
  Series I. Other Papers contains miscellaneous personal and family papers, including identification papers, sketchbooks, financial and legal records, and printed materials.
  - Copy of will & probate. Estate of John Poore (Box 54)
  - Correspondence, royalty statements, reviews, miscellaneous (Box 54)
  - Department of State, 2 (Box 54)
    Includes clippings and correspondence
  - Certificates and invoices (Box 54)
  - Boileau, Art poétique (Box 54)
  - Sketchbooks, 4 (Box 54)
  - Sketchbooks (continued), 6 (Box 55)
  - Sketches and drawings, 4 (Box 55)
  - Identity card (Box 55)
  - Printed material, 2 (Box 56)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2 (Box 56)
  - Gibraltar Chronicle (Box 56)
  - Quit claim deeds (Box 56)
  - Map of Spain and Portugal (Box 56)
  - Flower album (Box 56)
- Oversize, 0.25; (1 box)
  - Sketches and drawings (from Series V), 2 (Box 57)
  - Photographs (from Series IV), 14 (Box 57)